I've decided to proceed with radiation
treatment.
What's next?
Once a radiation treatment
plan has been made,
the planning process begins.
This involves gathering any related
imaging studies,
such as previous MRI's or Pet CT scans,
or obtaining an updated one if necessary.
The primary planning step is called a CT
simulation scan.
This is where you come into the radiation
oncology department
to get a special CT scan that is used
for radiation treatment purposes.
This scan is different from a regular CT
you may have gotten in the past.
For the CT simulation scan,
You will meet the team of radiation
therapists.
They are specially trained professionals
who are experts in acquiring this scan
and in operating the radiation treatment
machines.
The therapist will position
you on a CT scanner table
in a special way, depending on what
you are getting treatment for.
This may involve creating a special mask
in the shape of your head and face,
or creating bolsters or pillows shaped
to your body,
or positioning your arms and legs at
specific angles
all depending on your unique situation.
Once you are positioned,
the therapist use stickers
or other indicators
to mark specific locations on your body,
and will take photos
to record the exact method of set up.
This is important
as the position will be replicated
each time you receive radiation treatment.
Then you will undergo a CT scan
in this special position.
Again, depending on your specific plan,
you may receive other special instructions
such as how to breathe
during the scan itself,
or you may need a special dye or contrast
to help with illuminating your anatomy.
Once the CT scan is complete,
you will go home.
No radiation
treatment is given on this planning day.
This planning CT scan will be used
in conjunction with your previous images,
if applicable, to determine the radiation
treatment target
and will be used for the radiation
treatment planning.
Planning usually takes up to one week
and includes rigorous checks
with the doctors and medical physics team
for quality assurance to ensure a safe
and accurate delivery of the radiation.